<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mary Behrend Dedication Speech</title>
            <author ref="Behrend_Mary">Mary Behrend</author>
            <meeting>Speech was said to the Founders of Penn State Behrend, Board Members, Students,
               and Guests </meeting>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Lindsey Wood on <date when="2023-11-06">11-06-2023</date></p>
            <!--ebb: Let's find a way to include the URL for your GitHub repo in here
            using <ptr target="Your-GitHub-Repo, or GitHub Pages Website URL"/>
            -->
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>TALK GIVEN BY MRS. BEHREND AT THE DEDICATION OF BEHREND CENTER <date
                        when="1948-10-30">OCTOBER 30, 1948</date></p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <handDesc>
                     <handNote xml:id="greenPen" medium="green ink pen">Unknown writer marking
                        corrections on the typescript.</handNote>
                  </handDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>text from a typewriter in black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>TALK GIVEN BY MRS. BEHREND AT THE DEDICATION OF BEHREND CENTER OCTOBER 30, 1948</head>
         <p n="1"><persName ref="Milholland">President Milholland</persName>,<persName
               ref="Keller_Dr">Dr. Keller</persName>, <persName ref="Ferguson_Mr">Mr.
               Ferguson</persName>, Members of the various boards of Behrend Center, Students and
            Guests:</p>
         <p n="2">This day of the dedication is a very important one for both my daughter and
            myself. We often have had in mind aver since we were left with <placeName
               ref="Glenhill_Farm">Glenhill Farm</placeName> that it should be used if at all
            possible for a school or some place of some educational purpose. Over a number of years
            I tried to accomplish this. It could have been sold for a gambling place, a development
            program, several low offers came for a residence site (usually with the plan to divide
            it in one way or another.)</p>
         <p n="3">Last spring, when I returned from California, I stopped off in <placeName
               ref="Erie">Erie</placeName> and saw several protects. While in the midst of this here
            at the farm, I noticed, two visitors walking along over by the pool. So I went out and
            said to them, "I am Mrs. Behrend. Can I do anything for you?" <persName ref="Keller_Dr"
            /> and <persName ref="Henzi_Mr"/> presented themselves and Dr. Keller said they were
            looking around for a spot to locate an Erie center for Pennsylvania State College. I
            took them all around the place. Dr. Keller knew what was needed and his questions and
            remarks were very much to the point. After an hour, he asked if he could call up State
            College. Then things moved along. I went back East knowing that Pennsylvania State
            College wanted to buy the farm. It seemed so very right that it should be used in
            connection with an established college.</p>
         <p n="4">There were details to be worked out, there were numerous long distance calls with
            my lawyer, <persName ref="Gifford_Mr">Mr. Gifford</persName>, in Erie. What impressed me
            was the fact that State College wanted it enough to buy it, to endeavor to raise a
            goodly amount on top of what they could pay--quite a program. They thought well enough
            of it to want to buy it.</p>
         <p n="5">After several days, I said to my daughter, "I think this is something that would
            be a wonderful memorial to Father--something he almost could have planned himself. I
            think I should give it all to the college.</p>
         <p n="6">And that is how it came about.</p>
         <p n="7">Looking back over many years, I know I was able to make two important and very
            right decisions. The first in <date when="1907">1907</date> when I consented to marry
            Ernst Behrend. The second decision was, as you may guess, to make this outright gift to
            Pennsylvania State College of Glenhill Farm as a memorial to my husband. It is just 50
            years since the ground was broken for the Hammermill Paper Company.</p>
         <p n="8">It seems suitable that such a memorial should be maintained in Erie. <persName
               ref="Behrend_Ernst">Ernst Behrend</persName> did not only head the Hammermill Paper
            Company, but had time for various civic duties and was active on several boards in this
            city. He was president to the <placeName ref="Hamot_Hospital"/> for several years. These
            duties he took seriously as indeed he did his citizenship. He tried to put his best into
            whatever he undertook.</p>
         <p n="9">Everyone connected with the Center has been kind and considerate and, what pleases
            me so much, so appreciative of the beauty of the build- ings and the surroundings. It is
            gratifying to observe the care with which all details have been worked out in accordance
            with the architect's original work. And the use which has been made of all spaces is
            little short amazing. I am sure had there been any hen houses and large dog kennels, Mr.
            Ferguson would have had them enlarged a bit and some members of the faculty would now be
            living in them. Maybe not with twins but just couples!</p>
         <p n="10">I want to express my thanks to the editors of the Nittinay Cub, the Center's
            publication, for the very nice article about me which they printed. The magazine is
            cleverly figured out and I congratulate them I used to publish a small magazine many
            years ago, the Grasshopper, 250 Only to say I still love the smell of printers' ink and
            beleive I could soon catch on to setting type once more.</p>
         <p n="11">I would like to shake hands with <persName ref="Burt_Grace">Grace Burt</persName>
            and <persName ref="Bebko_Donald">Donald Bebko</persName>, the first young people from
            the Hammermill to take the courses at Behrend Center</p>
         <p n="12">When I first visited Erie back in 1905 and 1906, I met Ernst Behrend. I came out
            to visit <persName ref="Carter_Maud">Maud Carter</persName> (now Mrs. Shannon and head
            of the <orgName ref="RedCross">Red Cross</orgName>) and I am happy she is here today.
            She will remember that just before the first dinner party the men we were to meet were
            being described to us and I was asked by whom would you like to sit? And I replied, "I
            think I would like to sit beside the paper man-he seems the nicest, " and he was.</p>
         <p n="13">During these visits, I met his parents. They came in those days every summer and
            spent three months in Erie. <persName ref="Brust_Mrs_Will">Mrs. William
            Brust</persName>, a sister now living in Erie, always came with them. Mrs. Brust, I am
            happy to say is here today.</p>
         <p n="14">The Mother was a dependable and lovely person and made many friends in <placeName
               ref="Erie">Erie</placeName>. The Father was one of the most interesting men I have
            ever met. Not particularly tall, with a shock of snow white hair, and fine intelligent
            face, he presented an appearance not to be forgotten. His mind was keen. His manner of
            unfolding a problem always fascinated me--even if I did not entirely understand what it
            would be all about--I would always listen with rapt attention. He never seemed to use an
            extra word, each sentence was a definite part of the whole. And then he had a loveable
            and whimsical way of tucking in little jokes and there would be a twinkle in his
            eye!</p>
         <p n="15">These parents of <persName ref="Behrend_Ernst">Ernst Behrend</persName> were a
            dependable factor when it came to making my decision to leave my family, relatives in
            New England, and "go west.</p>
         <p n="16">During the first years of our married life, we lived almost in the mill yard with
            the switching engines snorting past the front porch. Interesting years-visitors from all
            over the world it seemed: <placeName ref="Norway">Norway</placeName>, <placeName
               ref="Sweden">Sweden</placeName>, <placeName ref="England">England</placeName>,
               <placeName ref="Germany">Germany</placeName>, <placeName ref="Austria"
               >Austria</placeName>, <placeName ref="Argentina">the Argentine</placeName>,
               <placeName ref="Brazil">Brazil</placeName>, etc., etc.</p>
         <p n="17">When our two children were old enough to travel they accompanied us on our
            cruises and tours--twice around the world and to the West Indies several times, South
            America and so on.</p>
         <p n="18">Wherever we went <orgName ref="Ham">Hammermill</orgName> agents always welcomed
            us and, while we may have missed many sights while being entertained by these kindly
            people, we did make many good friends. To some of these I' have recently mailed
            newspaper clippings about this memorial to Ernst Behrend in Erie and have had wonderful
            letters in return.</p>
         <p n="19"><rs ref="Behrend_Ernst">My husband</rs>, like <rs ref="???">his Father</rs>, had
            a pleasant, cheery way of meet- ing people and the same little twinkle in his eye. Few
            people today seem to have twinkles--we need more in this battered up old world.</p>
         <p n="20">Many things happened--I cannot talk about it all. But there came a time in our
            lives when we were sad and bewildered. It was then that we bought this farm and over the
            years built up the place more or less as you see it today. <persName
               ref="JCAinsworth_Mr">Mr. J. C. Ainsworth</persName>, who many of you will remember as
            the head of the physical department at the Y.M.C.A., took us first to see the location.
            We came out here often and had picnics. We used to take long walks through the woods and
            later had some western ponies we rode. There were always many dogs--we both liked them.
            (I am glad there are dogs here now.) Many happy years were spent at <placeName
               ref="Glenhill_Farm"/>. We three loved it all</p>
         <p n="21">My husband always had time to talk with young people and to be of help to them to
            the best of his ability. I remember hearing him say more than once that it meant more to
            him to feel that young people were <q>making good</q> in the mills than to read balance
            sheets with profit figures. No matter how busy he was, there was always time in his day
            to listen to the problems young people would bring to him.</p>
         <p n="22">I feel grateful that the opportunity to make this gift came exactly as it did. It
            will further one of his greatest interests- education--to be carried on where loved best
            to be-Glenhill Farm.</p>
         <p n="23"><add hand="greenPen">"</add>It is pleasant to feel that, over the years to come,
            many young men and women will go forth from this lovely spot well equipped <del
               rend="strikethrough" hand="greenPen">from</del>
            <add hand="greenPen" place="right">with</add> the <del rend="strikethrough"
               hand="greenPen">instruction</del>
            <add hand="greenPen" place="left">education</add> they have received<add hand="greenPen"
               >"</add> at the <placeName ref="BC">Behrend Center of the Pennsylvania State
               College</placeName>. </p>
         <p n="24">Thank you.</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
