<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Mr. Potter</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="2023-11-17">November 17th,2023.</date></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>Letter written by Mr.Wilson to Mr. Potter. <date
                     when="1948-03-26">March 26, 1948</date></p>
               </msContents>
            </msDesc>
            
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p> cc: <persName>M.M. Boring</persName>,<orgName type="company">Schenectady Works</orgName></p>
         <p>bc: <persName>D.B Pugh</persName></p>
         <p><persName>E.W Nick</persName></p>
         <p><persName>R.P. Wright</persName></p>
         <p><persName>G.H.Sturgis</persName></p>
         <p>reference 3-F 3-b</p>
         <p><date when="1948-03-26">March 26th 1948</date></p>
         <p><persName>Dr. A.A. Potter</persName>,<affiliation type="education">Dean of Engineering</affiliation></p>
         <p><orgName type="education">Purdue University</orgName></p>
         <p><placeName type="city">Lafayette,Indiana</placeName></p>
         <p>Dear <persName>Dr Potter</persName>:--</p>
         <p>in reply to your <date when="1948-03-16">March 16th 1948</date> letter addressed to <persName>Mr. G. W. Wilson</persName> it is apparent
            that you desire accurate information as it might apply to our company as a whole
            therefore since this information is directly available through the office of <persName>Mr. M.M.
               Boring</persName> at <orgName type="company">Schenectady</orgName> your inquiry is being forwarded to him for reply.</p>
         <p>For your information, <orgName type="education">Pennsylvania State College</orgName> is at present being petitioned to
            establish an undergraduate Center in <placeName type="city">Erie PA</placeName> to provide the initial to use of accredited
            college study to those interested in  engineering, science and agriculture. Despite
            opposition voiced by three local colleges namely <orgName type="education"> Mercyhurst</orgName>, and <orgName type="education">Villa Maria (girls
               college)</orgName>,and <orgName type="education">Gannon college</orgName>   (offering Liberal Arts courses), it has been determined
            through a carefully conducted survey in cooperation with <orgName type="education">Penn State College</orgName> Extension
            Services that there is a definite need for such a Center in this area we understand that
            the matter is to be discussed with the <orgName type="education">Penn State</orgName> Trustees during the coming week, and
            for the benefit of this largely Industrial community, we trust that a favorable decision
            to establish that you sent to you will be made.</p>
         <p>It would be far preferable to the people of this community as a whole to establish such
            a branch of <orgName type="education">Penn State College</orgName> which is thoroly competent to provide high standard
            instruction in these specialized subjects, rather than an attempt to add an engineering
            curriculum to the college above-mentioned.</p>
         <p>Fall particularly may be secured from <persName>Mr. David E. Pugh</persName> of <affiliation>Pennsylvania State College</affiliation>
            who has spent considerable time in this area studying the entire situation.</p>
         <p>Yours very truly,</p>
         <p>(Signed)<persName>R.C.Reed</persName> </p>
         <p>supervisor of personnel</p>
         <p> <persName>RCReed</persName>/h</p>

      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
