<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <!-- 2023-11-08 ebb: UPDATE THIS TEI HEADER to make sure they are equivalent / consistent across the project. Use MB_Dedication. (You don't have to have a handNote for every one of these.) -->
         <titleStmt>
            <title>1948-07-28 Advisory Board Meeting</title>
            <author>R.C. Henzi</author>
            <meeting>Advisory Board Metting to discuss changing the name of the campus and various
               other concerns.</meeting>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="2023-11-01">November 1st,2023.</date></p>
            <p><ptr target="https://github.com/sammoniot/FA23BehrendArchive"/>Our GitHub repo!</p>

         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>Advisory Board meeting that was held on <date when="1948-07-28">July
                        28th,1948.</date></p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>text from a typewriter in black ink. </typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <docAuthor>R.C. Henzi</docAuthor>

         <p><title>Minutes of the meeting for the Advisory Board for the Pennsylvania State College
               in Erie.</title></p>
         <p><time>Time: 4:00 P.M.,July 28,1948</time></p>
         <p>Place: <placeName type="education">The Behrend Center</placeName></p>
         <p>Those Members Present:</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. H.C Ogden</persName></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. C.Dean Klahr</persName> <persName type="attended">Mr. Edwin W. Nick</persName> <persName type="attended">Mr. R.C. Reed</persName>
            Mr. Bertram E. Claridge Mr. N.A. Carlson Mr. H.C. Mitchell Mr. G.R. Fryling Mr. Allyn
            Wright Mr. J.A. Zurn Mr. T.Reed Ferguson Mr. R.C. Henzi </p>
         <p>Visitor Present: Mr.E.L. Keller</p>
         <p>Members Not Present:Mr. W Pitt Gifford Mrs. Mary B. Behrend Mr. H.L.R. Emmet Dr. C.
            Herman Grose Mr. Ellis T. Knobloch Mr. J.O. Keller Dr. Paul H. Henkel</p>
         <p>Mr. E.W. Nick,President,called the meeting to order. He asked the Secretary to read the
            minutes of the previous meeting. Mr. Henzi read the minutes of the meeting.A motion to
            accept the minutes was made by Mr. Claridge and seconded by Mr.Zurn.</p>
         <p>Mr. E.W. Nick,President,called the meeting to order. He asked the Secretary to read the
            minutes of the previous meeting. Mr. Henzi read the minutes of the meeting.A motion to
            accept the minutes was made by Mr. Claridge and seconded by Mr.Zurn.</p>
         <p>Mr. Nick asked the Secretary to mail the minutes of all future meetings to each member
            of the Board.</p>
         <p>Mr. Nick asked Mr. Ferguson,Administrative Head,for a resume of the general situation at
            the Behrend Center.Mr. Ferguson covered the construction work to date and stated that
            the work is ahead of scheduele. Mr. Ferguson also brought the Advisory Board members
            up-to-date on the staff members appointed.</p>
         <p>On the matter of publicity,Mr.Ferguson commended the action of some companies in
            publicizing Behrend College in their company publications. He also stated that both of
            the local newspapers have been very cooperative.He talked briefly about concerning the
            Daytime technical Institute and Evening Technical Institute and cautioned that these
            activities not be overlooked as they are an integral part of the college program.Mention
            was made of the fact that new quarters would have to be found for the Evening Technical
            Institute. </p>
         <p>Mr. Nick suggested that the Board give encouragement to responsible organizations and
            civic groups to use the Behrend College facillities.</p>
         <p>Mr. Nick asked for a general discussion on the changing of the name of the Behrend
            Center.Mr. E.L. Keller suggested that one means might be for the Advisory Board to
            formally petition the Board of Trustees of the College for this change. It was pointed
            out that "Center" was the word used in the agreement between Mrs. Behrend and the
            College Trustees. At this juncture,Mr. Nick suggested that</p>
         <p>this terminology was only used as a matter of convience,and that Mrs. Behrend definitley
            wanted the name to be Behrend College,if that was at all possible. Some of the reason
            for changing the name to "College" are: (1) A matter of pride among the students in
            attending a college rather than a Center. (2) There are a number of institutions that
            use the word "Center" in their titles,thus leading to posdible confusion.(3) The natural
            couse of events might well be that the Pennsylvania State College will become a
            university,in which case "Behrend College" would be a logical name. Other views were
            offfered by members of the Board.</p>
         <p>It was moved by Mr. Fryling that the Erie branch be called "Behrend College" . This was
            seconded by Mr. Carlson and the motion was passed. It was agreed that the President of
            the Advisory Board write a letter to the Board of Trustees listing these valid reasons
            for this recommendation. It was further suggested that a letter from Mrs.Behrend also be
            sent to the Board of Trustees on the matter.</p>
         <p>The following night letter was sent to President Millholland that this petition could be
            sent to the Board of Trustees at their meeting at State College,Friday,July 30th. </p>
         <p>"ADVISORY BOARD AT BEHREND CENTER AFTER LENGTHY DICUSSION REQUEST CONSIDERATION BE GIVEN
            TO CHANGING NAME OF COLLEGE BRANCH IN ERIE TO BEHREND COLLEGE STOP ALL BOARD MEMBERS
            UNANIMOUS IN THIS REQUEST STOP SHE IS WRITING TRUSTEES TO THIS EFFECT E W NICK PRESIDENT
            ADVISORY BOARD"</p>
         <p>A more detailed letter was also to be mailed to President Milholland on this
            matter.(copy attached) </p>
         <p>A general discussion was held on the dedication set for September 11,1948,Saturday
            Afternoon.The president of the advisory board suggested the Judge Hirt be asked to give
            the acceptance speech in the name of the community.This suggestion was made as a motion
            by Mr.Zurn and seconded by Mr.Claridge. It was further suggested that Reverend Gearhart
            be asked to give the opening prayer.It was agreed to send personal invitations to all
            High School Principals in Erie County and to the Presidents of Colleges in the Erie
            area. </p>
         <p>Mr. Nick asked Mr. Keller for information on the enrollment for the first semester.Mr.
            Keller stated that there would be at least 150 students and 30 of these will be girls
            who will live on the Behrend campus in the second floor of the residence.This area will
            be made over into dormitory space. </p>
         <p>Mr. Robert Reed suggested that pieces of promotional materials at the plants be made
            available.Mr. Allyn Wright endorsed this heartily.Mr.Ferguson agreed to have this
            material placed in theirhands. He will have a quantity printed for use in various
            plants. </p>
         <p>A short discussion was held on the need for pianos at the center. The Advisory Board
            members were asked to do what they could toward securing these instruments. </p>
         <p>The meeting adjourned at 5:25 P.M.</p>
         <p>R.C. Henzi Secretary</p>
         <p>RCH:ci</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
