<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Minutes of the meeting for the Advisory Board for the Pennsylvania State College
               in Erie.</title>
            <author>R.C. Henzi</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="1948-07-07">July 7th,1948.</date></p>
            <p><ptr target="https://github.com/sammoniot/FA23BehrendArchive"/>Our GitHub repo!</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>The board reviewed the responsibilities of the different members.</p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>text from a typewriter in black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>

         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <milestone unit="page1"/>
         <p>Minutes of the meeting for the Advisory Board for the Pennsylvania State College in
            Erie.</p>
         <p>Time:4:30 P.M.,<date when="1948-07-07">July 7th,1948</date>.</p>
         <p><placeName type="business">Place:Board Room of the Manufacturers'
               Association</placeName></p>
         <p>Those Present:<persName type="attended">Mrs.Mary B. Behrend</persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr.Edwin Nick</persName><persName type="attended">Mr. R.C.
               Reed</persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. Bertram E. Claridge</persName><persName type="attended"
               >Mr. W.Pitt Gifford</persName>
            <persName type="attended"> Mr. N.A. Carlson </persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. H.C. Mitchell</persName>
            <persName type="attended"> Mr. G.R. Fryling</persName>
            <persName>Mr. Allyn Wright</persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. J.A. Zurn</persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. J.O. Keller</persName>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. Reed Ferguson</persName><persName type="attended">Mr. Dale
               Lindsey</persName><persName type="attended">Mr. R.C. Henzi</persName>  </p>
         <p>The meeting was informally called to order by <persName type="attended">Mr. R.C. Reed</persName>. Mr. Reed expressed his
            appreciation of the work done by all the members of the original committee. In the name
            of this group,<persName type="attended">Mr. Reed</persName> thanked  <persName type="attended">Mrs. Behrend</persName> for her most generous gift of the <placeName type="farm">Behrend farm</placeName>
            ,given to the <placeName type="education">college</placeName> as a memorial to her husband,the late <persName
               ref="Behrend_Ernest">Ernest R. Behrend</persName></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Reed</persName> introduced <persName>Mr. J.O. Keller</persName>,<affiliation type="education">Assistant to the President in Charge of Extension</affiliation>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. Keller's</persName> remarks concerning the duties and activities of an advisory group for such
            an educational facility as the present one.<persName type="attended">Mr. Keller</persName> offered the following list of
            members and officers of the <orgName type="education">Advisory Board</orgName>,as the College's appointment for the initial
            group. </p>
         <p><orgName type="education">ERIE ADVISORY BOARD</orgName></p>
         <p>Officers:</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr.Edwin Nick,</persName><affiliation type="company">Northern,Equipment Company,President (3 years)</affiliation></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. R.C. Reed,</persName><affiliation type="company">General Electric Company,Vice President,(3 years)</affiliation></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Bertram E. Claridge,</persName><affiliation type="company">Hammermill Paper Company,(3 years)</affiliation></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. R.C. Henzi,</persName><affiliation type="education">Secretary</affiliation></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs.Mary B. Behrend,</persName><address><addrLine> Porchuck Road, Greenwich,Conneticut </addrLine></address></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. W. Pitt Gifford,</persName>Attorney,<address><addrLine>615 Masonic Bldg.</addrLine></address>(3 years)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. N.A. Carlson,</persName>President,Erie Meter Systems (3 years)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. H.C. Mitchell,</persName>Retired,<address><addrLine>917 West 6th St.(2 years)</addrLine> </address></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. G.R. Fryling,</persName>President,<placeName>Erie Resistor Corporation (2 years) </placeName>
         <persName type="attended">Mr. Allyn Wright,</persName>Vice President,Reed Mfg. Company (2years)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended"> Mr. J.A. Zurn,</persName>Founder and Chairman,Zurn Mfg. Company (2years)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. H.L.R. Emmet, </persName>Works Manager,General Electric Company,(1
            year)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Ellis T. Knobloch,</persName>President,Union Iron Works,(1 year)</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Dr. Paul H. Henkel </persName>Vice President,Continental Rubber Works (1
            year)</p>
         <p>Ex Officio:<persName type="attended">Mr. J.O. Keller</persName>assistant to the president in Charge of
            Extension, <persName type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName>,administrative head</p>
         <p>honorary member: Mr. J.E. Reed</p>
         <milestone unit="page2"/>
         <p>Mr Keller in His official capacity expressed the deep appreciation of the college in
            acceptance of Mrs. Behrend's gift. Mr. Reed tuned the meeting over to Mr Nick, President
            of the Advisory Board. Mr. Nick went on record to the effect that he accepted the
            responsibilities of his position and recognized in it a chance to follow the educational
            opportunities this institution is able to provide for the citizens of
            Pennsylvania.Mr.Nick also told Mrs. Behrend of the sincere appreciation of The Advisory
            Group for her gift of the Behrend Farm to Erie. He made the statement that this event is
            the most important that has occured in Erie to its benefit in his lifetime.</p>
         <p>Mr. Nick asked the secretary Mr. R.C. Henzi to read the proposed bylaws to the board
            they are as follows:</p>
         <p>"The purpose of The Advisory Board is to further in any and all manners the best
            interest of the Behrend College of the Pennsylvania State College in Erie. Such
            advisement and counsel should be should keep in mind the fact that this facility is for
            the benefit of the people of the Commonwealth and particularly the community and
            surrounding area of Erie.</p>
         <p>The Advisory boards interest will include all types of service extended by the
            Pennsylvania State College such as credit class work; non-credit institute work, both
            day and evening classes; guidance, adult education in all of its applicable phases;
            industrial and business services and any other future phase of service the college might
            introduce.</p>
         <p>1. The Advisory Board shall consist of not more than 20 members there shall be two ex
            officio members, the Head of the Behrend College and the assistant to the president of
            the Pennsylvania State College in Charge of Extension. Their terms of office will be
            unlimited. There shall be 15 members of whom five are to be chosen each year for a for a
            term of three years. The president may appoint with board approval, three members for
            one-year term only. </p>
         <p>2. With the exception of the ex officio members no member can succeed himself for more
            than three consecutive, three-year terms.</p>
         <p>Suggested committee:</p>
         <p>1. Membership or Nominating committee </p>
         <p>2. Executive or Steering Committee</p>
         <p> 3.Information Committee</p>
         <p> 4. Building Committee</p>
         <p> 5. Scholarship Committee</p>
         <p> 6. Local Policy Committee</p>
         <p>Mr Nick proposed that Mrs. R.C. Ogden and Mrs. C. Dean Khlar be appointed a special
            Board members for one year term. Mr. Nick made the suggestion in the form of a motion
            which was seconded by Mr. J.A. Zurn.The motion was carried.</p>
         <milestone unit="page3"/>
         <p> In a general discussion, Mr. Reed raised the question of enrollment figures. Mr. Keller
            answered the budget figures were arranged on an enrollment of 200 persons. Mr . Hoffman
            the Dean of Admissions said that 75 or 100 could be expected at the Center. Mr. Keller
            also explained that this is in line with college policy as to how many students they
            take in the various centers. The Dean of Admissions, according to Mr. Keller will be
            asked to reconsider this minimum figure for the Behrend Center. </p>
         <p>Mr. Carlson suggested to the committee that it interest itself and sponsoring more
            activity in attempting an enrollment of 200 from the community of Erie. He suggested
            industrial publications be used to publicize this so that the readers of these
            periodicals might consider the center as the place to send their children. Mr.Reed
            endorsed this plan with enthusiasm.</p>
         <p>The meeting adjourned at 5:45 P.M.</p>


      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
