<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Mr. Wilson</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="2023-11-17">11-17-2023</date></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>Letter written by Dr. A.A. Potter,the Dean of Engineering to Mr. Wilson. <date
                        when="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date></p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>The text was written via typewriter with black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <docAuthor>Dr. A.A. Potter</docAuthor>
         <head>FN-205 COPY for M.M. Boring Schenectady Works GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY bc: D.B. Pugh
            E.W. Nick R.P. Wright Commonwealth of Pennsylvania G.H. Sturges JOINT STATE GOVERNMENT
            COMMISSION Of the General Assembly P.O. Box 61 Room 450 - Capitol Building Harrisburg
            March 16,1948 Mr. G.W. Wilson,Manager Transportation Division GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY
            Erie,Pennsylvania </head>
         <p>Dear Mr. Wilson: Study-Demand for Personnel at Post-High School Level I am assisting Dr.
            George A. Works,Director Post High-School,in connection with the study he is making of
            the demand for scientific </p>
         <p>and technical personnel in the fields of engineering and in the areas commonly referred
            to as "Technical Institutes." This study is the result of an Act passed in July 1947 by
            the General Assembly of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania authorizing The Joint State
            Government Commission to study personnel needs of different types. You can aid me in
            this study by furnishing me the following information:</p>
         <p>1. How many people does your industry employ?</p>
         <p>2. What percentage of your employees may be classed as working in technical
            occupations</p>
         <p>3. Of your employees in technical occupations how many are Engineers with a college
            degree in engineering or the equivalent?</p>
         <p>4. Of your employees in technical occupations how many are in occupations auxiliary to
            engineering such as draftsman,testers,inspectors, technicians and similar categories
            which ordinarily acquire these so-called technical Institute type of preparation that is
            employees in the same areas between the skilled crafts and engineering</p>
         <p>5. Of the engineers employed by your organization, what percentage or graduates from
            Pennsylvania engineering colleges?</p>
         <p>6. Do you feel that the engineering output of Pennsylvania colleges should be increased
            if so should additional engineering College facilities be made available by increasing
            the facilities of the present institutions,</p>
         <p>Mr. G.W. Wilson -2- March 16th,1948</p>
         <p>by adding new institutions, or by encouraging more of the existing Pennsylvania College
            not now offering engineering to start engineering programs of study</p>
         <p>7. Are the facilities in Pennsylvania adequate to meet the needs for technical employees
            in the area between the skilled Ccaftsman and are engineers? If not, what facilities
            should be made available in Pennsylvania for the so-called "Technical Institute" type of
            education? Where should such additional technical institutes be located?</p>
         <p>I am taking the liberty of writing to you and to other leaders in Pennsylvania industry
            and shall appreciate a reply to any of the questions about also any other information
            which may prove helpful to me an appraising in the adequacy of the facilities in
            Pennsylvania to meet the needs of industry for engineering personnel and for those with
            the technical institute type of preparation</p>
         <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
         <p>A.A. Potter Dean of Engineering</p>
         <p> AAP:MMG</p>
         <p>cc:-Dr. George A. Works</p>
         <p>P.S. PLEASE ADDRESS YOUR REPLY TO THIS LETTER TO:</p>
         <p>Dr. A.A. Potter Dean of Engineering 
            Purdue University 
            Lafayette, Indiana</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
