<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Erie, Pennslyvania <date when="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date></head>
         <p>Mr. J. O. Keller</p>
         <p>Assistant to the President in charge of Extension</p>
         <p>Pennslyvania State College</p>
         <p>State College, Pennslyvania</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Keller</p>
         <p>Some preliminary consideration has been given, we believe, to the advisa- bility of
            establishing an undergraduate center of Pennsylvania State College at Erie,
            Pennsylvania. Since the matter was first discussed, a number of developments have taken
            place which indicate the desirability of concisely restating our reasons for presenting
            our request, and to provide you with a statement of all the facts which will be of value
            in giving it your earnest corsideration.</p>
         <p>Evidence of Need:</p>
         <p>It is realized that evidence of the need of primary importance. Erie is not only growing
            rapidly in population at present, but it is also expected to continue to grow for
            several years.</p>
         <p>One principle reason for this conviction is due to the fact that the Goneral Electric
            Company, which is the largest local employer, has greatly expanded its facilities to
            employ many more people on a regular basis. Before World War II, it noramlly employed
            about 6000. This employment increased to a peak of 11,000 during the war. It numbers
            about 18,000 at present, which is three times as large as before the war, and this
            employment is expected to settle dowm to a figure of around 16,000. Conserva- tive
            estimates indicate that this increase will bring about a growth of around 50,000 in
            population in the next few years, over and above the presently esti- mated mumber of
            125,000. This will include the families of these employees, the butchers, bakers, store
            clerks, professional people and others which go to comprise all community services.</p>
         <!-- Stopped editting here; needs TEI and spell/word checked with the original document-->
         <p>Being very largely an industrial commanity, with over 100 diversified in- dustries,
            aurrounded by rich farm lands, it Is self-evident that educational facilities leading to
            degrees in sciences, engineering and agriculture are of considerable importance.</p>
         <p>To further check the ovidance of definite need, a quostionnaire ma pro- pared a yoar
            ago, with the counsel and assisteace of dr. David Be Pugh, of Pennsylvanta State
            Collogo, to determine, the number of high school undergraduates who would be interested
            in availing themselves of the first two years of college courses if an Undergraduate
            Centor of Pennsylvania State College were to be establiched here. All were requested to
            diseven the questions asked with their parents, and turn in their replies.</p>
         <p> These were the questions: 1.) Do you plan to go to college! (res or no): 8.) have you
            applied for enrollment in any collage? (Yes or no): S.) lave you.been accepted? (Yes or
            no); 4.) Nould you oomeider entering a college to be established in Brio and operated by
            the Pennsylvania State College? (res 20). Hame and address were optional,</p>
         <p>their report of the results indicated- 1. 173 atudents plan to go to college but were
            not interested in a Pennsylvania State college branch in Erte. 2. 245 do not plan to go
            to college but would be interested if there were a Pennsylvania State College branch in
            Brie. 3. 477 are going to oollege and are interestod in a Penneylvanie State College
            branch in Erie.</p>
         <p>The above would indicate that thero are a very substantial number of poten- tial
            enrollees who would be directly benefitted through the establishment of an Undergraduate
            Center here. In addition, many employees of local industries will definitely be
            intereated in accredited courses offered. Here these figures to be discounted 50% at the
            present time, it would still be conolusive aridence of definite interest and support of
            such a projeot. Since school enrollmente are increasing, it can be safely assumed that
            future interest will be even greater than indicated at present</p>
         <p>While discussing nod in Brie, it should also be pointed out that there is definite nood
            for ooedueational facilities which would permit women to enroll in preparation for the
            steadily inorensing number of technical fields nor open to</p>
         <p>Facilities to house an Undergraduate Center:</p>
         <p>Since from a practical standpoint, it would seem wiser to locate and rent existing
            Pacilities until the success of the center ere assured, the desirabili- ty of
            eatablishing such a Center in Brie was presented to the rombers of the Spie Sohool Board
            at their noting held January 15, 1940, and suggesting that school building not presently
            needed for clessroom work be made avallable, on a tomporary basis. Funds for necessary
            rearrangerent of, and imgrovenent in, the building were assured, so as to cause the
            Board no expence. At their rest regular monthly meeting, the proposal was violently
            opposed by representatives of Gannon College of Erie, who incorrently stated that atx
            ares colleges objected. These were listed ast- Cannon College, Wereyhorst Colloge, Villa
            lacie Colloge, Pollen Alliance College, Bainboro State Teacher College, and Allegheny
            College.</p>
         <p> Loither Edinboro nor Allegheny were authorized to comment officially, and have since
            repudiated the misleading statements made concerning their attitude towards the
            proposal. It is indeed unfortunate that data secured sone tine ago for an entirely
            difforent purpose was used to give the impression that there is no present need for high
            caliber instruction faoilities in the frie Community, in addition to the already
            excellent Ilberal arts courses botug offored.</p>
         <p>The request for a school butlding was donied, on the basis that the School Board
            required the use of the building for storage purposes; it would entell great exponse to
            move the furniture; and that the Board 1s only interested in aduoational matters
            affecting grade school and high school pupile. This posai- bility is thorofore
            definitely ruled out in the city of Erie for the present.</p>
         <p>however, mny, civic groups, such as the Business and Professional Monon' Club, the
            League of Women Voterd, the Brie City Counoil of P.T-A., as well as many groups of
            interested citizens have evidenced a growing conviotion of the need, in writing, and
            have insisted that the projeet be actively purgued in spite of the objections raised by
            those interosted in preserving a monopoly of existing facilities.</p>
         <p>Therefore, as the result of further investigation, we now have the assurance of
            unanimous cooperation from the School Board of a tounship adjacent to Erie, who have
            offered the free use of an area of several acres alongside a large High School the use
            of their auditorium, gymmusium, and procurement facilities; and in case of tenporary
            need while construetion is being completed, the use of classroom facilities after 3:30
            P.l.</p>
         <p> It is confidently known that the Brie Community will be able to raise the funds
            necessary to construet a modest building to accommodate approximately 400 students,
            laboratory failities, library, and offices. This building would be crected on the site
            offered, and would be considered a decided ascet to the community.</p>
         <p>Summary:</p>
         <p>1. The need for the facilities offered by a coeducational indergraduate Center such as
            now provided in other communities of the Stato by the Pennsylvania State College, has
            definitely been established in the Erie Community.</p>
         <p>2. 'Adequate fallitien will be provided in a receptive community adjacent to Erie, and
            reached by City bus service.</p>
         <p>3. Barly consideration on the part of those in charge of Extonaion-- Ponnsylvanie State
            College--la mort earnestly requested towards the establishment of an Undergraduate
            Center in the Brie Community,</p>
         <p>Active work ia desiguing the failities, or raising nocessary funde is held In abeyance
            pending word from Pennsylvania State college. It is our sincore hope that favorable
            consideration will be given and that advice to proceed may be recoived in time to
            complete the project ready for enrollments in September 1948.</p>
         <p>Respectfully, R. C. Reed R. C. Reed, hcting Chairman Supervisor of Personnel, ceneral
            Electric Co.</p>
            <!--Signatures and text need added from page 4-->
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
