<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Mr. Wilson</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="2023-11-17">11-17-2023</date></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>Letter written by Dr. A.A. Potter,the Dean of Engineering to Mr. Wilson. <date
                        when="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date></p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>The text was written via typewriter with black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <docAuthor>Dr. A.A. Potter</docAuthor>
         <milestone unit="page1"/>
         <head>FN-205 COPY for <persName>M.M. Boring</persName>
            <orgName type="company">Schenectady Works</orgName>
            <orgName type="company">GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</orgName> bc: <persName>D.B. Pugh</persName>
            <persName>E.W. Nick</persName>
            <persName>R.P. Wright</persName> Commonwealth of Pennsylvania <persName>G.H.
               Sturges</persName>
            <orgName type="government">JOINT STATE GOVERNMENT COMMISSION Of the General Assembly</orgName>
            <address>
               <postBox>P.O. Box 61 Room 450 - Capitol Building Harrisburg</postBox>
            </address>
            <date when="1948-03-16">March 16,1948</date>
            <persName>Mr. G.W. Wilson</persName>,<affiliation>Manager Transportation
               Division</affiliation>
            <orgName type="company">GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY</orgName>
            <placeName type="City">Erie,Pennsylvania</placeName>
         </head>
         <p>Dear <persName>Mr. Wilson</persName>: Study-Demand for Personnel at Post-High School
            Level I am assisting <persName>Dr. George A. Works</persName>,<affiliation>Director Post
               High-School</affiliation>,in connection with the study he is making of the demand for
            scientific </p>
         <p>and technical personnel in the fields of engineering and in the areas commonly referred
            to as <q>Technical Institutes</q>. This study is the result of an Act passed in <date
               when="1947-07">July 1947</date> by the <orgName type="government">General Assembly of
               the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania</orgName> authorizing 
            <orgName type="government">The Joint State Government Commission</orgName> to study personnel needs of different types. You
            can aid me in this study by furnishing me the following information:</p>
         <list>
            <item n="1">How many people does your industry employ?</item>
           
            <item n="2">What percentage of your employees may be classed as working in technical
               occupations?</item>
            <item n="3">Of your employees in technical occupations how many are engineers with a college
               degree in engineering or the equivalent?</item>
            <item n="4">4. Of your employees in technical occupations, how many are in occupations auxiliary to
               engineering, such as draftsman, testers, inspectors, technicians, and similar categories
               which ordinarily require these so-called <q>Technical Institute</q> type of preparation? That is,
               employees in the same areas between the skilled crafts and engineering.</item>
            <item n="5">Of the engineers employed by your organization, what percentage are graduates from
               Pennsylvania engineering colleges?</item>
            <item n="6">Do you feel that the engineering output of Pennsylvania colleges should be increased?
               If so, should additional engineering college facilities be made available by increasing
               the facilities of the present institutions, <milestone unit="page2"/> by adding new institutions, 
               or by encouraging more of the existing <placeName type="state">Pennsylvania</placeName> College
               not now offering engineering to start engineering programs of study?</item> 
            <item n="7">Are the facilities in <placeName type="state">Pennsylvania</placeName> adequate to meet the needs for technical employees
               in the area between the skilled Ccaftsman and are engineers? If not, what facilities
               should be made available in <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName> for the so-called <q>Technical Institute</q> type of
               education? Where should such additional technical institutes be located?</item>
         </list>
        
       <!--2023-11-30 ebb: Let's put this formwork information (printed letterhead info) up in the TEI header so it doesn't interrupt the meaningful flow of content
          in the letter. <fw>Mr. G.W. Wilson <date when="1948-03-16">March 16th,1948</date></fw>
       -->
         
         <p>I am taking the liberty of writing to you and to other leaders in <placeName type="state">Pennsylvania</placeName> industry
            and shall appreciate a reply to any of the questions about also any other information
            which may prove helpful to me an appraising in the adequacy of the facilities in
            <placeName>Pennsylvania</placeName>  to meet the needs of industry for engineering personnel and for those with
            the technical institute type of preparation</p>
         <p>Very sincerely yours,</p>
         <p><persName>A.A. Potter</persName><affiliation>Dean of Engineering</affiliation> </p>
         <p>AAP:MMG</p>
         <p>cc:-<persName>Dr. George A. Works</persName></p>
         <p>P.S. PLEASE ADDRESS YOUR REPLY TO THIS LETTER TO:</p>
         <p><persName>Dr. A.A. Potter</persName><affiliation>Dean of Engineering</affiliation>  <orgName type="education">Purdue University</orgName> <placeName type="city">Lafayette, Indiana</placeName></p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
