<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE ADVISORY BOARD.DECEMBER 29,1948</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Samantha Moniot on <date when="2023-11-28">November 28th,2023</date></p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library</repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <msContents>
                  <p>Letter written by Dr. A.A. Potter,the Dean of Engineering to Mr. Wilson. <date
                        when="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date></p>
               </msContents>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>The text was written via typewriter with black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <body>
         <milestone unit="page1"/>
         <p><title>MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF <orgName type="education">THE ADVISORY BOARD THE
                  PENNSYLVANIA STATE COLLEGE BEHREND CENTER</orgName>
               <placeName type="city">ERIE,PA</placeName></title></p>
         <p>A meeting of <orgName type="education">The Advisory Board for the Pennsylvania State
               College Behrend Center</orgName>, <placeName type="city">Erie Pa.</placeName> was
            held on Wednesday,<date when="1948-12-29">December 29th, 1948</date> at <time
               type=" afternoon">4:00 P.M.</time> at the <placeName type="education"
               >Center</placeName>.</p>
         <p>Those members present were:</p>
         <p><persName type="attended"> Mr. E. W. Nick</persName>
         </p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. H.C. Ogden</persName><persName type="attended">Mr. G.R.
               Fryling</persName>
         </p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. C.D. Klahr</persName><persName type="attended"> Mr. N. A.
               Carlson</persName></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. J.A. Zurn</persName><persName type="attended"> Mr.Allyn
               Wright</persName></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. H.C. Mitchell</persName><persName type="attended"> Mr.W.
               Pit Gifford</persName></p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. E. T. Knobloch</persName><persName type="attended"> Mr. T.
               Reed Ferguson</persName></p>
         <p>
            <persName type="attended">Mr. B. E. Claridge</persName><persName type="attended"> Mr.
               R.C. Henzi</persName></p>
         <p>Visitor present: <persName type="attended">Mr.S.H. Campbell</persName></p>
         <p>Members not present: <persName type="absent">Mr. R.C. Reed</persName></p>
         <p>
            <persName type="absent">Mrs. Mary B Behrend</persName></p>
         <p>
            <persName type="absent">Mr. H.L.R. Emmet</persName>
         </p>
         <p>
            <persName type="absent">Dr.C Herman Grose</persName></p>
         <p>
            <persName type="absent">Dr. Paul Henkel</persName>
         </p>
         <p><persName type="attended"> Mr. E W Nick</persName>,<affiliation>president</affiliation>
            ,called the meeting to order. A motion was made and seconded that the minutes of the
            last meeting not be read.</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Nick</persName> asked <persName type="attended">Mr.
               Ferguson</persName> for a general report on all activities today at the <placeName
               type="education">Center</placeName>. <persName type="attended">Mr.
               Ferguson</persName> gave the details of the building program and pointed out that it
            was now completed with exceptions of a few minor jobs he added that the money expended
            to date was an excess of the expected <measure type="dollars">60,000.00</measure> and
            when all bills are in a will probably approximate <measure type="dollars"
               >100,000.00</measure>.</p>
         <p>The Administrative Head informed the board the third are 152 credit students and between
            80 to 100 evening technical students in attendance at <placeName type="education"
               >Behrend Center</placeName>. In addition there were also two graduate courses being
            offered who's enrollment constitutes over 40 local school teachers.</p>
         <p> SOCIAL EVENTS-- for the benefit of those who will not present,-- <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName> briefly outlined the activities that
            transpired at the</p>
         <listEvent>
            <event when="1948-10-30">
               <label>formal dedication of Behrend Center.</label>
            </event>
         </listEvent>
         <p> He pointed out that the center was also being used by other groups which is as was
            originally planned search groups as the <orgName type="education">Erie County Principals
               Association</orgName> have held their dinner meetings at the <placeName
               type="education">center</placeName>
            <listEvent>
               <event type="music">
                  <label>a cello concert</label>
               </event>
            </listEvent> was given by a member of the local <orgName type="music">Philharmonic
               Association</orgName>. The Faculty held a <listEvent>
               <event type="food">
                  <label>dinner</label>
               </event>
            </listEvent> prior to Christmas Vacation after which an amateur program was put on by
            the students of the <placeName type="education">Center</placeName>. The students held
            their Christmas dance at the<placeName type="ballroom">Masonic Building
               Ballroom</placeName> .</p>
         <p>
            <persName type="attended">Mr.Ferguson</persName> informed <orgName type="education">the
               board</orgName> that the <placeName>Center</placeName> would be able to take in a few
            new students in February and at the present there are about 12 applications on hand. He
            further predicted that the fall 1949 enrollment was expected<milestone unit="page2"/> to
            be around 350 students.</p>
         <p>The new catalog for the fall term would be available about the <date when="1949-03-01"
               >1st of March.</date></p>
         <p>The registration for evening classes, second term, was also discussed by <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName> and he mentioned the fact that it was planned
            to include a few courses that would be new to the program such as Spanish, Russian and
            Public Speaking. <orgName type="education">The Board</orgName> was brought up to date on
            the work that will be done in a <placeName type="health">Speech Clinic</placeName> in
            conjunction with the <orgName type="health,government">State Office of
               Rehabilitation</orgName> and they will also told about the plans to assist the
               <orgName type="education">Erie Parent Teaches Association</orgName> in the operation
            of a Forum.</p>
         <p>GENERAL DISCUSSION ON <persName type="attended">MR. FERGUSON'S</persName> REMARKS--
               <persName type="attended">Mr. Nick</persName> asked as to the status of new second
            semester enrollees after having completed this half year's work. <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName> pointed out these students must, upon
            registration, sign an agreement that they will, through attending <placeName
               type="education">summer school</placeName>, prepare themselves so that they can enter
               <placeName type="education">school</placeName> in the fall as a full-fledged
            sophomore. </p>
         <p>The question was raised as to whether or not present facilities could accommodate the
            predicted 350 student enrollment for the fall 1949 term. It was pointed out that this
            was based on the assumption that necessary expansion of present classrooms would be
            made.</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Carlson</persName> asked what the possibilities were for
            offering graduate work through the <placeName type="education">Behrend Center
               facility</placeName> , particularly for area school teachers. It was indicated that
            the student that certain persons on the campus or working on this problem with the idea
            to provide more than the present three credit limit of graduate work for the benefit of
            some of the Board members it was briefly explained that the present College policy does
            not permit their recognizing more than three credits towards a master's degree on the
               <placeName type="education">Penn State campus</placeName> in spite of the fact that
            student other colleges will accept more than three extension graduate credits offered by
               <orgName type="education">Penn State</orgName> services. It is expected that this
            three credit limit will be increased in the not too distant future but at present it is
            not known just how many credits will be allowed.</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName> then suggested that <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Henzi</persName>give <orgName type="education">the
               Board</orgName> a report on the recreation and athletic activities carried on at the
               <placeName type="education">Center</placeName>. <persName type="attended">Mr.
               Henzi</persName> stated that's a program at present was a comparatively modest one,
            and due in part to the inadequacy of the present facilities and to the fact that we are
            still much in the process of original organization. The board was told that
               <persName>Mr. Marvin Demp</persName>, <affiliation>Recreational Director
            </affiliation>at the <placeName>Center</placeName>, was directly in charge of this work
            and under existing circumstances, was doing an excellent job. The various activities, in
            addition to the regular required physical education program, are as follows:</p>
         <p>MEN'S ACTIVITIES-- Intramural Basketball, six complete teams. It is planned to pick a
            representative team from these teams to play other comparable Fresh-men groups at nearby
            institutions. These games are played in the evening at the <placeName type="education"
               >Lawrence Park High School Gymnasium</placeName> and also on a <placeName
               type="religious">church gymnasium floor</placeName></p>
         <p>There are approximately 15 to 20 men students who spend Saturday mornings under
               <persName>Mr. Demp's</persName> direction, in wrestling. It is not expected to have
            an organized wrestling team at the <placeName type="education">Center</placeName> but
            this group will have gained considerable experience in the event that they are
            interested in wrestling as a varsity sport once they are admitted to the <placeName
               type="education">main campus.</placeName></p>
         <milestone unit="page3"/>
         <p>The Center operates a bowling league in which over<num>60</num> persons participate one
            day a week. The comment was made that this is rather exceptional since it represents a
            little better than half of the student body. The participants in this activity are both
            men and women students and also a few of the faculty. It does much towards heightening
            the general morale of the Center and makes for a better relationship between student and
            faculty. <persName type="attennded">Mr. Henzi</persName> also gave an outline of the
            expected winter sports program which includes skiing and ice skating. He told the Board
            that <persName type="attended">Mr. Lamb</persName> of the <orgName type="government"
               >Erie Dispatch</orgName> had donated <num type="dollars">$100.00</num> to the ski
            club. This money will be used to buy the equipment necessary to construct a ski lift. An
            area has also been prepared for ice skating and water will be run into the prepared pond
            once freezing weather sets in.</p>
         <p>GIRL'S ACTIVITIES: The girls activities are somewhat limited by equipment and numbers.
            However, smaller groups have become interested in such sports as archery, golf and
            horseback riding. The outdoor pool of course is not available most of the time because
            of the weather. It was used quite extensively doing the short period in which sports
            could be carried on. </p>
         <p>DISCUSSIONS ON SCHOLARSHIPS:-- <persName type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName>
            suggested that more scholarships could be used at the <orgName type="education"
               >Center</orgName>. He informed the board that approximately <num type="percentage"
               >90%</num> of the dropouts the <orgName type="education">center</orgName> has had to
            date has been because of financial difficulties. He further suggested that the
            industrial work scholarship would be good i.e. where a company would guarantee to
            provide a certain number of work hours in order that a needy student might earn money
            towards his college expenses. <persName type="attended">Mr. Carlson</persName> made the
            statement that he was 100% for this but felt the present time was somewhat inopportune
            for further solicitations. This comment was made in view of the recent ending of a
            number of heavy and intensive financial drives made in the local community.</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. Klahr</persName> suggested that a loan fund might be set
            up in order to help deserving students. At this point<persName>Mr. Claridge</persName>
            announced that the Hammermill Trust Fund will have a third scholarship available
            starting in <date when-custom="2/49">February</date>. The board received this news with
            the many expressions of enthusiasm.</p>
         <p><persName type="attended">Mrs. Ogden</persName> informed the Board that <orgName
               type="education">The College Women's Club</orgName> has a Loan Fund for women and
            that she was sure this would be available for proven deserving cases.<persName
               type="attended">Mr. Ferguson</persName> then said the center will be very glad to use
            this the source if necessary there was some discussion as to operation of this very
            necessary work and it will suggested that the presently named scholarship committee be
            changed to the student aid committee this suggestion was put into a form of a motion by
               <persName type="attended">Mr. Fryling</persName> and seconded by <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Claridge</persName>. Motion was carried. The president of the
            board was directed to name the members to this reorganized committee at an early
            date.</p>
         <p>PROPOSED FELLOWSHIP-- <persName type="attended">Mr. Nick</persName> reported to the
            board that <persName type="absent">Mr. L.G. Meyer</persName> of <orgName type="company"
               >PA Meyer and Sons</orgName> wants to establish a Chair for Merchandising and
            Retailing at the <orgName type="education">Behrend Center</orgName>. <persName
               type="attended">Mr. Nick</persName> asked both <persName type="attended">Mr.
               Ferguson</persName> and <persName type="attended">Mr. Campbell</persName> what
            information was available to pass on to <persName type="absent">Mr. Meyer</persName> as
            to such matters as cost acceptance by the college and other details concerned in such a
            move. Mossrs. Ferguson and Campbell both agreed that they would have to have more
            information before being able to give <persName type="absent">Mr.Meyers</persName>
            definite facts. It was decided that these gentlemen would make an appointment to
               see<persName type="absent">Mr.Meyers</persName> concerning further details. They
            would then have to clear through the main campus before final action could be taken on
            this matter. It was, however, felt that no serious difficulty would be encountered and
            making this most generous gesture to become a reality. After details have been worked
            out, a further report will be made to <orgName type="education">The Advisory Board</orgName>.</p>
         <milestone unit="page4"/>
         <p>TECHNICAL INSTITUTE PROGRAMS--Mr. Campbell told the board of Purdue Universities
            Cooperative program with the Inland Steel Corporation in which workers from this company
            went to school one day a week and took technical institute type subjects. These courses
            are not college credit courses but are generally college level and their content. They
            are much more specific and their objectives and give the individual information on a
            particular job rather than the general background of knowledge we received in a complete
            four year college program. This work is taken with the company paying the expenses of
            the students. Mr. Campbell was interested in knowing whether the board felt that such a
            program might be of interest to local industries. It was decided that Mr. Fryling who is
            presently the president of the Manufacturers' Association Board would determine if this
            group is interested in such a project. If the Association Board so decided Mr. N.A.
            Hedden will come to Erie to give them more details of this program.</p>
         <p>Mr. Ferguson asked for the Board's opinion on industrial plants registratiors for
            Evening Technical Institute Classes he pointed out that this was to be done at the
            General Electric Plant the way the plan would operate would be for a company to announce
            that on a certain day, at a certain time, representatives from the Center would be
            available to the company employees to furnish information on the evening classes and
            also to take registrations for enrollment in these courses. Mr.Fryling agreed to also
            check this matter with the Manufacturers' Association and pass their reaction onto the
            Board. Mr. Campbell informed the board that the Erie Technical Institute was at present
            one of the smallest in the state and he was of the opinion that a community the size of
            Erie, whether it's diversified industries, should have more people involved in this type
            of training.</p>
         <p>PROPOSED TWO-YEAR COLLEGE CREDIT SECRETERIAL COURSES--Mr. Ferguson asked the advice of
            the Board regarding a proposed two-year secretarial course to be given at the Behrend
            Center. Mr. Ferguson's primary concern was asked to whether or not local business
            colleges would object to the inauguration of this course. This question was best
            answered by expressions to from members of the board that in spite of local secretarial
            training available they invariably had to give training to new office employees before
            such persons were deemed competent to carry on the company's business. The Board was
            definitely in favor of such a course of study being offered at the Center. Mr. Ferguson
            made the remark that objection might be overruled by the fact that our facilities would
            limit the number of enrollees to approximately 50 students. This program of study has to
            receive the college Senate approval to become official but this action is expected at
            the next meeting of this group.</p>
         <p>FUTURE BUILDING PLANS-- Mr. S.H. Campbell from the College campus in charge of community
            services was asked to present a suggested plan for a new building to the Board. Mr.
            Campbell did this by giving a brief history of the recent action taken at the Hazleton
            Center on a very similar structure. All of the members present was shown a blueprint of
            a proposed recreational building for the Behrend Center. Mr. Campbell pointed out that
            this was a necessary facility toward the completeness of any college campus and that it
            was used for many more things than sports activities. He pointed out such groups as
            dramatics, musical organizations, assemblies of any large size all needed such an area
            to carry on the programs. He further stated that it was hoped to introduce, in the not
            far distant future, an ROTC unit for the Behrend Center but that this would be
            impossible until it could be proven to the military authorities that an adequate place
            for indoor drill was available. Such a recreation building as this would serve that
            purpose admirably.</p>
         <milestone unit="page5"/>
         <p>Mr. Campbell was asked what the estimated cost of this building might be and his reply
            was to the effect that approximately $75,000.00 would be necessary. There was then a
            general discussion on whether or not the board would want to get a community
            organization or organizations to sponsor a drive for funds to erect such a building. It
            was the general consensus of opinion that if this be done it would be better if a group
            of organizations sponsored the move. It was felt that the board as such would not direct
            this drive but would attempt to interest local community organizations to take the lead
            in this work.</p>
         <p>Mr. Carlson offered a motion that a committee the appointed to contact such
            organizations to ascertain their interest in a conducting such a drive as described
            above. This was seconded by Mr. Zurn and the motion was carried. This committee will be
            appointed by the President of the Board.</p>
         <p>The President of the Board suggested that this group go on record in a message of
            condolence to the family of Mr. J. Elmer Reed, whose very recent death was such a loss
            to the board and the community. Mr. W Pitt Gifford moved that such an expression be made
            for the Behrend Center Advisory Board to the Reed family. This was seconded by Mrs.
            Klahr the motion was carried Mr. Nick appointed Mr. Claridge as a Chairman and Mr.
            Gifford and Mr. Ferguson as the members to carry this motion. (Note:) a copy of the
            above mentioned resolution was attached to each set of minutes which was sent to the
            members.</p>
         <p>ADJOURNMENT--A motion was offered to adjourn the meeting. It was moved, seconded and
            carried. The meeting ended at 5:45 p.m.</p>
         <p>Respectfully submitted</p>
         <p>R.C. Henzi</p>
         <p>RCH:HA R.C. Henzi, Secretary</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
