<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/behrendFoundODD.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Letter to Mr. Keller from R. C. Reed</title>
            <author ref="Reed_RC">R.C. Reed</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoded by Lindsey Wood on <date when="2023-12-06">12-06-2023</date>
            </p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <msDesc>
               <msIdentifier>
                  <repository>Penn State Erie, The Behrend College Lilley Library<ptr
                        target="https://github.com/sammoniot/FA23BehrendArchive"/></repository>
               </msIdentifier>
               <physDesc>
                  <typeDesc>
                     <typeNote>text from a typewriter in black ink.</typeNote>
                  </typeDesc>
               </physDesc>
            </msDesc>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <head>Erie, Pennslyvania <date when="1948-03-16">March 16, 1948</date></head>
         <p><persName ref="Keller_Dr">Mr. J. O. Keller</persName></p>
         <p>Assistant to the President in charge of Extension</p>
         <p><placeName ref="PSC">Pennslyvania State College</placeName></p>
         <p>State College, Pennslyvania</p>
         <p>Subject: Request for consideration of an <placeName ref="Erie">Erie</placeName>
            Undergraduate Center</p>
         <p>Dear Mr. Keller</p>
         <p>Some preliminary consideration has been given, we believe, to the advisability of
            establishing an undergraduate center of Pennsylvania State College at Erie,
            Pennsylvania. Since the matter was first discussed, a number of developments have taken
            place which indicate the desirability of concisely restating our reasons for presenting
            our request, and to provide you with a statement of all the facts which will be of value
            in giving it your earnest consideration.</p>
         <p>Evidence of Need:</p>
         <p>It is realized that evidence of the need of primary importance. Erie is not only growing
            rapidly in population at present, but it is also expected to continue to grow for
            several years.</p>
         <p>One principle reason for this conviction is due to the fact that the <orgName ref="GE"
               >General Electric Company</orgName>, which is the largest local employer, has greatly
            expanded its facilities to employ many more people on a regular basis. Before World War
            II, it noramlly employed about 6000. This employment increased to a peak of 11,000
            during the war. It numbers about 18,000 at present, which is three times as large as
            before the war, and this employment is expected to settle dowm to a figure of around
            16,000. Conservative estimates indicate that this increase will bring about a growth of
            around 50,000 in population in the next few years, over and above the presently esti-
            mated mumber of 125,000. This will include the families of these employees, the
            butchers, bakers, store clerks, professional people and others which go to comprise all
            community services.</p>

         <p>Being very largely an industrial community, with over 100 diversified industries,
            surrounded by rich farm lands, it is self-evident that educational facilities leading to
            degrees in sciences, engineering and agriculture are of considerable importance.</p>
         <p>To further check the evidance of definite need, a questionnaire was prepared a year ago,
            with the counsel and assistance of <persName ref="Pugh_Mr">Mr. David B. Pugh</persName>,
            of Pennsylvanta State College, to determine the number of high school undergraduates who
            would be interested in availing themselves of the first two years of college courses if
            an Undergraduate Center of Pennsylvania State College were to be established here. All
            were requested to discuss the questions asked with their parents, and turn in their
            replies.</p>
         <p>These were the questions: 1.) Do you plan to go to college? (Yes or no); 2.) Have you
            applied for enrollment in any college? (Yes or no); 3.) Have you been accepted? (Yes or
            no); 4.) Would you consider entering a college to be established in Erie and operated by
            the Pennsylvania State College? (Yes or no). Name and address were optional.</p>
         <p>A total of 2800 such questionnaires were distributed to potential enrollees in Erie High
            Schools through the cooperation of the School Administrative Office, their report of the
            results indicated:-</p>
         <p>1. 173 students plan to go to college but were not interested in a Pennsylvania State
            College branch in Erie.</p>
         <p>2. 245 do not plan to go to college but would be interested if there were a Pennsylvania
            State College branch in Erie.</p>
         <p>3. 477 are going to college and are interestod in a Pennsylvania State College branch in
            Erie.</p>
         <p>The above would indicate that there are a very substantial number of potential
            enrollees who would be directly benefitted through the establishment of an Undergraduate
            Center here. In addition, many employees of local industries will definitely be
            interested in accredited courses offered. Were these figures to be discounted 50% at the
            present time, it would still be conclusive evidence of definite interest and support of
            such a project. Since school enrollments are increasing, it can be safely assumed that
            future interest will be even greater than indicated at present.</p>
         <p>While discussing need in Erie, it should also be pointed out that there is definite need
            for coeducational facilities which would permit women to enroll in preparation for the
            steadily increasing number of technical fields now open to women.</p>
         <p>Facilities to house an Undergraduate Center:</p>
         <p>Since from a practical standpoint, it would seem wiser to locate and rent existing
            facilities until the success of the center were assured, the desirability of
            establishing such a Center in Erie was presented to the members of the <orgName ref="SchDst">Erie School Board</orgName>
            at their meeting held <date when="1940-01-15">January 15, 1940</date>, and suggesting that a school building not presently
            needed for classroom work be made available, on a temporary basis. Funds for necessary
            rearrangement of, and improvenent in, the building were assured, so as to cause the
            Board no expense. At their next regular monthly meeting, the proposal was violently
            opposed by representatives of Gannon College of Erie, who incorrectly stated that six
            area colleges objected. These were listed as:- <orgName ref="GC">Gannon College</orgName>, <orgName ref="MC">Mercyhurst College</orgName>, <orgName ref="VMC">Villa
            Maria College</orgName>, <orgName ref="PAC">Polish Alliance College</orgName>, <orgName ref="ESTC">Edinboro State Teachers College</orgName>, and <orgName ref="AC">Allegheny
            College</orgName>.</p>
         <p>Neither Edinboro nor Allegheny were authorized to comment officially, and have since
            repudiated the misleading statements made concerning their attitude towards the
            proposal. It is indeed unfortunate that data secured some time ago for an entirely
            different purpose was used to give the impression that there is no present need for high
            caliber instruction facilities in the Erie Community, in addition to the already
            excellent liberal arts courses being offered.</p>
         <p>The request for a school butlding was denied, on the basis that the School Board
            required the use of the building for storage purposes; it would entail great expense to
            move the furniture; and that the Board is only interested in educational matters
            affecting grade school and high school pupils. This possibility is therefore
            definitely ruled out in the City of Erie for the present.</p>
         <p>However, many civic groups, such as the <orgName ref="BPWC">Business and Professional Women's Club</orgName>, the
            League of Women Voters, the <orgName ref="ECCPTA">Erie City Council of P.T.A.</orgName>, as well as many groups of
            interested citizens have evidenced a growing conviction of the need, in writing, and
            have insisted that the project be actively pursued in spite of the objections raised by
            those interested in preserving a monopoly of existing facilities.</p>
         <p>Therefore, as the result of further investigation, we now have the assurance of
            unanimous cooperation from the School Board of a township adjacent to Erie, who have
            offered the free use of an area of several acres alongside a large High School; the use
            of their auditorium, gymnasium, and procurement facilities; and in case of temporary
            need while construction is being completed, the use of classroom facilities after 3:30
            P.M.</p>
         <p>It is confidently known that the Erie Community will be able to raise the funds
            necessary to construct a modest building to accommodate approximately 400 students,
            laboratory facilities, library, and offices. This building would be erected on the site
            offered, and would be considered a decided asset to the community.</p>
         <p>Summary:</p>
         <p>1. The need for the facilities offered by a coeducational Undergraduate Center such as
            now provided in other communities of the State by the Pennsylvania State College, has
            definitely been established in the Erie Community.</p>
         <p>2. Adequate facilities will be provided in a receptive community adjacent to Erie, and
            reached by City bus service.</p>
         <p>3. Early consideration on the part of those in charge of Extension--Pennsylvania State
            College--is most earnestly requested towards the establishment of an Undergraduate
            Center in the Erie Community,</p>
         <p>Active work in designing the facilities, or raising necessary funds is held in abeyance
            pending word from Pennsylvania State College. It is our sincere hope that favorable
            consideration will be given and that advice to proceed may be received in time to
            complete the project ready for enrollments in September 1948.</p>
         <p>Respectfully,</p>
         <p>R. C. Reed</p>
         <p><persName ref="Reed_RC">R. C. Reed</persName>, Acting Chairman</p>
         <p>Supervisor of Personnel, General
            Electric Co.</p>
         <p>E.W. Nick</p>
         <p><persName ref="Nick_EW">E.W. Nick</persName>, President</p>
         <p><orgName ref="NEC">Northern Equipment Company</orgName></p>
         <p>R.P. Wright</p>
         <p><persName ref="Wright_RP">R.P. Wright</persName>, Secretary</p>
         <p><orgName ref="RMC">Reed Manufacturing Company</orgName></p>
         <p>G. H. Sturgis</p>
         <p><persName ref="Sturgis_GH">G. H. Sturgis</persName>, Superintendent (retired)</p>
         <p>General Electric Company</p>
        <p><persName ref="Gifford_Mr">W. P. Gifford</persName></p>
         <p>Attorney at Law</p>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
