<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <p>MINUTES OF THE MEETING OF THE ADVISORY BOARD THE PENNSYLVANIA STATE COLLEGE BEHREND
            CENTER ERIE, PA.</p>
         <p>A luncheon meeting of the Advisory Board for The Ponnoylvania State Collage, Behr ond
            Center, Erie, Pa, was held on Monday, April 11, 1949 at 12:15 p. m. the Center.</p>
         <p>Those members present were:</p>
         <p>Dr• C. Herman Grose Mr, • E. To Knobloch Mrs. C. Dean Klahr Mrs. H. C. Ogden Irr Ga R •
            Fryling Mr. H. C. Mitchell Mr• B. E. Claridge Mr• Robert Reed Mr • Allyn Wright Mrs.
            Mory B. Behrend Mr. I. Reed Ferguson fir. R. C. Henzi</p>
         <p>Visitors Present:</p>
         <p> Mr• E. L. Keller • S. H. Campbell Mr • K. L. Holderman Mr. Othmar Wuenschel</p>
         <p>Members not present:</p>
         <p>Mr. He L. R. Emmet Mr M. A. Carlson Mr. W. Pitt Gifford lir. J. A. Zurn Dr • Paul H.
            Henkel Mr. E. W. Nick</p>
         <p>Mr. Robert Reed, Vice-President, called the meeting to order and expressed appreciation
            for the nice lunch and welcomed all visitors to the meeting.</p>
         <p>Mir. G. R. Fryling offered the motion that the minutes of the previous meet- ing be
            accepted. The motion carried. Reading of tho minutes was foregono since all members had
            received copies.</p>
         <p>Mr. Reed expressed his, and his family's, appreciation for the letter of condolence sent
            on his father's death.</p>
         <p>The Administrative Head, Mr. Ferguson, gave a brief report of the activ- ities covering
            the following points:</p>
         <p>L. The second semester enrollment is 160 freshmen, of which 30 are new students.</p>
         <p>2. 100 course enrollments in the Evening Technical Instituto.</p>
         <p>3. Two graduate Extension courses, with enrollments of twenty each. They are: "Safety
            Education" and "Modern Tendencios In American Education.'</p>
         <p>4. A Motor Fleet Supervision course is in operation in Warren, with an enrollment of
            twenty porsons.</p>
         <p>5. 11r. Goorgo Harvoy is conduoting two fly-tying classos in Erio, and on in Sharon,
            with total onrollmont of 61 porsons.</p>
         <p>G. A Spooch Corrootion Clinic is boing conductod at tho Contor by Mr. Tilliom Horoan and
            throo individuals aro roooiving training through tho Stato Rohabilitation Buroau. Mr.
            Forguson furthor statod that sinoo tho inauguration of this sorvico many of tho froshmon
            havo roquostod holp in spooch and readingo</p>
         <p>7. Many clubs and sociotios havo boon making use of the Contor to hold their rogular
            mootings. Tho Administrative Hood said that this was to be onoouragod as Bohrond Contor
            should bo availablo to any worthy community group.</p>
         <p>8. Mr. Balmor, Chomistry Instructor, is in charge of a radio program ovory Saturday at
            6:30 p. me, under tho auspicos of the American Chemioal Socioty.</p>
         <p>9. The Contor holpod tho Erie Paronts Toachors Association con- duct a Forum in which
            mombers of tho local and campus staff participated as speakors.</p>
         <p>10. All high schools in the area have beon visited for the pur- pose of informing
            graduating seniors as to what is available at Tho Ponnsylvania State College and,
            particularly, Behrend Center. Thoso intorested in attonding college wore givon
            applications.</p>
         <p>11. An Open Houso will bo hold April 28th and 29th, at which timo high school studonts
            from the surrounding arca arc invited to inspoct Behrend Conter. Mr. Ferguson added that
            ho hopod that all of the Board mombors would be able to visit the Conter at that
            time.</p>
         <p>12. Wir. Forguson pointod out that vory littlo has been done in the way of a radio
            program from the Contor because tho staff has not had the time to do a rally good job.
            It is hoped that soothing will bo done in telovision noxt Fall,</p>
         <p>Mr. Rood asked what tho prosent status was in scholarships at the Contor. Ho was told
            that at prosent thero are thro Hamunermill scholarship studonts, one Senatorial
            Scholarship student and one Wosloyville Rotary Club Scholarship studont. He askod what
            had boon dono on the Student Aid and Loan Fund. It was pointod out that Mr. Carlson was
            Chairman and sinco ho was not prosent roport could not bo made on that project at this
            timo.</p>
         <p>Mrs. Ogdon commonted that tho College Womon's Club now has over $1,000.00 available for
            this purposo, providod a logitimato need is establishod. There was a goneral discussion,
            in which Mr. E. L. Kollor and Mrs. Behrend, and others took part on how tho college
            might receive a scholarship. It was sug- gestod that approximatoly $400.00 is nocossary
            for a scholarship at Bohrond Contor. Mr. Keller mado the statoment that generally tho
            amount and period oovored by any scholarship was entiroly up to tho donor.</p>
         <p>It was roported that Mr. L. G. Moyor had been contaoted on his Morchandis- ing
            Followship idea and that based on that discussion, tho College is prosontly working on
            dotails of how this might bo sot up,</p>
         <p>To dato thoro has not boon official Sonato action on tho proposod two your socrotorial
            courso. It is oxpoctod that this notion will bo forthooming so that this courso of study
            may bo offorod at tho Contor in tho Fall of 1949</p>
         <p>As a mombor of tho Committoo on funds for a Rocroation Hall, Mr. Rood roportod that ho
            and Mr • Claridgo and Mr. Knobloch had mot sovoral timos. Among tho things that thoy
            discussod and folt should bo rocommondod woro a long range plan for a building layout on
            tho campus. The Committeo wants holp from tho Collogo in making such a gonoral layoute
            It was folt that work should bo dono first on that building most noodod immodiatoly. It
            was suggostod that funds might bost bo raisod by tho Alumni Association of Tho
            Ponnsylvonia Stato Collogo in Erio. With this in mind, Mr. Othmar Wuonschol, Prosidont
            of tho Alunni Association was askod to sit in on tho mooting. At this point Mr.
            Muonschol romarkod that he plannod to call togothor somo of tho key mombors of tho
            Alumni Association, following tho closo of this Advisory Board Mooting, sinco ho would
            thon bo in possossion of additional facts. Ho furthor suggost- od that in order to put
            such a campaign ovor it might bo woll to havo somo at- tractive skotchos and layouts of
            tho proposod building to show to prospoctive contributors.</p>
         <p>Mr. Rood stated that ho did not fool it nocossary that a high pressure cam- paign bo put
            on in ordor to raiso this monoy. Mr. Kollor suggostod that tho Rocroation Building would
            be an oxcollent projoct for tho idvisory Board sincc the Collego must nocossorily bo
            first and primarily concorned with adoquato facilities for study. Ho motioned
            spocifically additional noods in the scionce Building. His basis for this romark was tho
            anticipation of approximatoly 300 studonts for tho Fall of 1949 which is doublo thoso
            hero prosontly; and, also, the possibility within tho noxt yeor or two of tho addition
            of a sophomoro class. Ho furthor statod that the Collogo will go to work on a plot plan
            for a long range building program.</p>
         <p>Mr& Keller informed tho Board tho collego has spent $113,000.00 to date on the Bohrond
            Contor and expocts to invost anothor $40,000,00 for this Fall It was statod that the
            possibilities at Bohrend Centor scomed groator than thoso at other Contors and,
            thoroforo, moro funds must be allocated. Mrs. Bohr ond told the Board that sho had
            rocontly visited the Architocts at Phil- adolphia who built tho prosontly namod Behrond
            Contor. Sho suggested that porhaps this architect might be all right for such a plonning
            progrom.. Mrs. Bohrond folt that the Ponnsylvania Dutch stylo of architecture ought to
            be maintainod throughout in any additions that would be mado, At this point Mr Koller
            told Mrs. Behrond and othor mombors of tho Board, that in any evont all such plans would
            havo to bo passod on by tho Colloge architects, Mrs. Bohrond thon made the vory gonorous
            offor of $1000.00 if such financial aid would bo nocossary in order to get the projoct
            of a campus plan underway. Mr, E, Le Koller, for the Colloge, and Mr. Rood for the
            Board, both oxprossod their approciation at this offer. Dotails of this matter have to
            bo workod out in tho noar future.</p>
         <p>Mr. Koller was asked to givo an ostimato on the cost of tho Rocreation Building and ho
            offored tho figuro of $75,000,00 as a minimum, Such a build- ing would bo availablo for
            the ontiro community and not just tho Conter. Mr, Knobloch suggested that in the dosign
            of this building the thought bo kopt in mind for future oxpansion. Mr. Kollor addod that
            tho Rocroation Building location must of nocossity be docidod by available playing fiold
            space and what the drainago program might be. Mr. Rood asked Mr. Ferguson to toll tho
            Board the amount that was sot up for noxt your's budgot. Mr. Forguson's answor was that
            $245,000.00 had boon allottod.</p>
         <p>Mr. Forguson statod that ovor 150 applications aro at prosont out in tho hands of
            possiblo froshmon studonts. It was of intorost to know from Mr. Kollorts romark that as
            of tho ond of March tho Colloge has roceivod ovor 5,000 applications for ontranco in tho
            Froshman Class, This roprosonts 1,000 more than appliod last yoar. lir. Rood mado tho
            statomont that ho beliovod a largo numbor of local studonts will bo onrollod at Bohrond
            Contor in Soptombor 1949,</p>
         <p>Mr. Forgus on roported that Mrs. Bohrond had vory graciously loaned throo paintings to
            the Conter to bo hung on our, at prosont, somewhat boro walls,</p>
         <p>The Board recoivod with much intorost, the information from Mr. Forguson that tho
            Student Council had inauguratod a survey of studonts and parents to dotormine tho number
            who would like to return to Bohrend Contor noxt yoor for thoir Sophomore work.</p>
         <p>The Student Council has sont cards to local alumni asking for donations of books for tho
            Library. The roturns on this roquost havo boon gratifying.</p>
         <p>Mrs. Behrond informed tho Board that sho would liko to rofurnish tho prosont library
            room with somo piocos of furniture that belongod to Mr. Bohrend porsonally and are now
            in the Hammermill Papor Company officos. This could bo dono sinco suggostod plans for
            additional facilitios this Fall include the moving of the prosent library to the
            classroom building. Mr. Keller pointod out that omphasis would bo placod on providing
            the Bohrend Center library with a number of scientific volumos that would bo of value to
            industry, as woll as the students; It is hoped that local industry can bo acquaintod
            with the matorial the library will possess so that thy may make use of it during the
            evonings.</p>
         <p>1 motion was mado and socondod for adjournmont at 2:05 p. m.</p> Rospoctfully submitted
         <!-- Fill in signature--> Re C. Honzi, Secrotary </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
